[英格兰 1842年]
沃尔特
Walter?
你不去和其他小朋友一起玩吗？
Don't you want to go and play with the other boys and girls?
他们都很友善的
They're very nice.
我才不需要其他人
I don't need anyone else.
他从来不跟别人说话
He never talks to anyone.
这孩子好孤僻
He's so alone.
这样下去不行的
It's not right.
这样不健康
It's not healthy.
我不想跟他们说话 他们太蠢了
I don't want to talk to them. They're silly!
他们太蠢了
They're silly.
不要跟他们说话 他们太蠢了！
Don't talk to them. They're silly!
不需要其他人
Don't need anyone else.
我可以帮你
I can help you.
怎么帮？
How?
[50年后]
最后降下的一批也已经取过样了
The last of the arrivals have been sampled.
庞大的族群正在靠近
The great swarm is approaching.
人类欢庆之日 也是其终结之时
As humanity celebrates, so shall it end.
最后的工序能准备好吗？
Will the final piece be ready?
正在准备着
It's in hand.
我将一如既往地为您效劳
I serve you in this, as in everything else.
你能守住秘密吗 今晚那些工人的事？
And do you keep my secrets -- those men who helped us tonight?
不成问题
Won't be a problem.
我答应过会喂他们的
I promised to feed them.
麻烦问一句 西敏博士
I beg pardon, Dr. Simeon ...
我们都工作一整天了 可我没看到任何食物啊
It's been a long day. I don't see any food here.
我可看到了
I do.
这是什么怪物？
What is this?
我说过要喂“你们”
I said I'd feed you.
不过我可没说是哪个“你们”
I didn't say who to.
玫瑰与王冠酒馆
The Rose & Crown
这个雪人是你堆的吗？
Did you make this snowman?
不是
No.
那是谁堆的？
Well, who did?
刚才还没有呢
'Cause it wasn't there a second ago.
它就这样凭空冒出来了
It just appeared, from nowhere.
也许这是以前降下的雪
Maybe it's snow that fell before.
也许它还记得怎么堆雪人
Maybe it remembers how to make snowmen.
什么 有记忆的雪么？这想法够傻的
What, snow that can remember? That's silly.
傻有什么错啊？
What's wrong with silly?
没什么 我不还在跟你这傻子说话么？
Nothing. Still talking to you, ain't I?
你叫什么名字？
What's your name?
克拉拉
Clara.
克拉拉 好名字
Nice name, Clara.
一定要留着这个名字
You should definitely keep it.
告辞了！
Goodbye!
喂！
Oi!
你去哪儿？我以为咱俩才互相认识呢
Where are you going? I thought we were just getting acquainted.
那是过去的我
Those were the days.
驾！
H'yah!
噢 看到你又提起兴趣了 真是让人耳目一新呢！
Oh, how refreshing to see you taking an interest again!
那姑娘怎么样？
Was she nice?
我只是跟她说两句话而已
I just spoke to her.
毫无疑问 你又给人产生了深刻的印象
And made your usual impact, no doubt.
瞎说 什么印象都没有
No, no impact at all.
以前的日子已经一去不复返了
Those days are over.
你控制不住自己的
You can't help yourself!
每回都是同一个套路
It's the same story every time.
而且总是以同样的两个词开篇
And it always begins with the same two words.
她不可能找到我的
She'll never be able to find me again.
她都不知道我叫做博士！
She doesn't even have the name -- Doctor!
哪儿来的两个词？
What two words?
博士？
Doctor?
Doctor who?
什么博士？
神秘博士
2012年圣诞特别篇
雪人来袭
编剧：史蒂文·莫法特
晚上好 老爷
Good evening, sir.
池塘又结冰了
Pond's frozen over.
那晚之前从来没有结冰过
Hasn't frozen since the night ...
你说的是一年前 你孩子的家庭老师死去的那晚
Since the night your children's governess died, a year ago.
老爷 是西敏博士 他坚持要等你回来
Dr. Simeon, sir. He insisted on waiting.
她就溺死在这个池塘里 后来池塘就冻上了
She drowned in this very pond, which then froze.
一个月之后冰才融化 那时你才发现了她的尸体
You didn't find her till a month later, when the ice finally melted.
我记得这件事 这种事情自然难以忘记
I recall the incident. It is the sort of thing one remembers.
冰也记得
The ice remembers, too.
你到底是什么人？来这里干什么？
Who are you? What do you want here?
拉提莫上校 这个池塘是你的
The pond is yours, Captain Latimer.
不过等池中之物长成的时候 我们就要把它取走
But what is growing inside it, when it is ready, is ours.
祝您晚安
Good evening.
西敏博士啊 你这么晚了还出门
Well, Dr. Simeon, you're out very late tonight.
不禁让人怀疑你去做什么了
Almost makes you wonder what you've been up to.
不过话说回来 我本来就经常琢磨
But then, I have often wondered
西敏博士和他的秘密研究所 到底在从事些什么活动
about the activities of Dr. Simeon and his exceptionally secretive institute.
看来我今晚真是三生有幸啊
Well, I am honoured this evening.
居然遇到了传说中的蒙面神探 和她笨拙的助手
The veiled detective and her fatuous accomplice.
很乐意为您效劳
At your service.
几乎可以肯定的说 柯南·道尔博士就是
You realise Dr. Doyle is almost certainly
以你们的事迹为原型 创作了他异想天开的小说
basing his fantastical tales on your own exploits?
当然 部分细节有所出入
With a few choice alterations, of course.
我十分怀疑《海滨杂志》的读者们能够接受
I doubt the readers of The Strand magazine would accept
他们伟大的侦探实际上是…
that the great detective is, in reality ...
一个女人
a woman.
还有她亲密得可疑的同伴…
And her suspiciously intimate companion ...
我很反感你这拐弯抹角的言辞！
I resent your implication of impropriety!
我们已经结婚了
We are married.
你有点缓不过来了吧
More than can be said for you, eh, dear?
回到正事儿 你不觉得这雪很有意思吗？
Now, then, this snow is interesting, don't you think?
这些冰晶似乎拥有低级心灵感应场
The ice crystals seem to have a low level telepathic field,
就好像能够感应
almost as if it can detect and respond to
周边人的思维和记忆
the thoughts and memories of the people around it.
拥有记忆的雪 能够学习的雪
Memory snow -- snow that learns.
真是异想天开！
How fascinating!
但愿它没有落入错误的人手中
I hope it's listening to the right people.
否则可能会成为一件可怕的武器吗 你觉得呢？
It could be a terrible weapon in the wrong hands, don't you think?
我认为冬天要来了
I think winter is coming,
这个世界闻所未闻的寒冬
such a winter as this world has never known,
它会是人类的最后一个冬天
the last winter of humankind.
你知道我为什么告诉你们这些吗？
Do you know why I'm telling you all this?
愿闻其详
I am intrigued.
因为你没有任何机会阻止它的到来
Because there is not a single thing you can do to stop it.
也许我不行 但我知道一个人可以！
Perhaps I can't, but I know a man who can!
那我很期待见到他
I look forward to meeting him.
你说的是博士吗？
Do you mean The Doctor?
可他是不会帮我们的
He won't help us!
他再也不帮忙了
He never helps any more.
这你也清楚
You know that.
是的 亲爱的 我确实了解
Yes, my dear, I do.
所以还是祈祷奇迹出现吧 我想这次我们真的会需要他
So pray for a miracle, because I think we are going to need him.
那帮人对全伦敦的雪人取样了
They've taken samples from snowmen all over London.
您觉得他们是在做什么呢？
What do you suppose they're doing in there?
这是一种全新的雪 可能是外星物种
This snow is new, possibly alien.
当你发现一种全新的事物
When you find something brand-new in the world,
一种前所未有的东西
something you've never seen before,
你接下来会去寻求什么呢？
what's the next thing you look for?
手榴弹？
A grenade?
是利润！
A profit!
那才是维多利亚时代的价值观！
That's Victorian values for you!
我提议进行一次全方位的正面攻击
I suggest a full frontal assault
使用自动激光猴子 解剖刀地雷 和强酸！
with automated laser monkeys, scalpel mines and acid!
为什么？
Why?
我们至少调查一下不好吗？
Couldn't we at least investigate?
这又不关我们的事
It's none of our business.
长官 我请示表达对您近期冷漠态度的反对
Sir, permission to express my opposition to your current apathy?
批准
Permission granted.
长官 我反对您近期的冷漠态度
Sir, I am opposed to your current apathy.
谢谢你 Strax
Thank you, Strax.
我何时真的需要听从一个精神错乱的矮土豆的建议的话
And if I'm ever in the need of advice from a psychotic potato-dwarf,
你肯定会第一个知道的
you'll certainly be the first to know.
可如果这雪真的是新出现的外星物种的话
But if the snow is new and alien,
我们难道不是应该设法摧毁它吗？
shouldn't we be making some attempt to destroy it?
请好好想想啊！
Be reasonable!
这不是我们要担心的问题
It is not our problem.
经历了这上千年拯救宇宙的日子以后 Strax
Over a thousand years of saving the universe, Strax,
你知道我学到了什么吗？
you know the one thing I learned?
宇宙根本不在乎
The universe doesn't care.
现在 我们还有自己的问题要操心
Now, we have a problem of our own to worry about ...
放我出去！喂！
Let me out! Oi!
别担心 我们不会伤害你的
Don't worry. No one's going to hurt you.
那是什么玩意儿？
What is that thing?
肃静 小子！
Silence, boy!
那位是Strax 如你所见 他容易犯糊涂
That's Strax and as you can see, he's easily confused.
肃静 姑娘！
Silence, girl!
不好意思啊 伙计
Sorry, lad.
他是桑塔人 克隆战士的种族 批量生产 每次造出一个军团
Sontaran -- clone warrior race, factory produced, whole legions at a time.
对他来说 两种性别有点数不过来了
Two genders is a bit further than he can count.
长官 请不要在敌方的女孩面前谈论我的繁殖过程！
Sir, do not discuss my reproductive cycle in front of enemy girls!
太尴尬了
It's embarrassing.
典型的六百万兄弟中的一个
Typical middle child of six million.
那你又是谁？
Who are you?
这不重要 因为你马上就会忘记我们
It doesn't matter because you're about to forget that you and I ever met.
我们需要那只虫子
We'll need the worm.
遵命 长官
Sir.
你们要用什么？什么样的虫子？
You'll need the what? The 'worm' worm?
别担心 不会疼的
Don't worry. It won't hurt you.
它只要碰一下皮肤 你就会失去一个小时的记忆
But one touch on your bare skin and you lose the last hour of your memory.
东西在哪呢？
Where is it?
什么在哪儿呢 长官？
Where's what, sir?
我让你去取记忆虫子
I sent you to get the memory worm.
是吗？什么时候？这小子是谁？
Did you? When? Who's he?
我们怎么在这儿？
What are we doing here?
看 下雪了呢！
Look, it's been snowing!
你又忘了用防护手套吧
You didn't use the gauntlets, did you?
我为什么要用防护手套呢？
Why would I need the gauntlets?
您是不是要我去取记忆虫子？
Do you want me to get the memory worm?
喂 你看到了没有？
Well, can you see it?
我觉得我听见它的叫声了
I think I can hear it.
喂！别想逃跑 待好别动
Oi! Don't try to run away. Stay where you are.
我干嘛要跑啊？
Why would I run?
我已经预料到接下来会发生什么了 一定很有意思
I know what's gonna happen next, and it's funny.
有什么好玩的？
What's funny?
噢 你这位小伙计 他还真是个丑陋的小家伙 是吧？
Oh, your little pal, for a start. Ugly little fella, isn't he?
也许吧 可他曾经为救我的一个朋友而牺牲过
Maybe. He gave his life for a friend of mine once.
那为什么他还活着？
Then how come he's alive?
我另一个朋友又把他救回来了
Another friend of mine brought him back.
但是我不确定他的智商是不是全回来了
I'm not sure all his brains made the return trip!
我看也是
Neither am I.
我看到它了！
I can see it!
噢！你够得着吗？拿到了没有？
Oooh! Can you reach it? Have you got it?
拿到什么了 长官？
Got what, sir?
因为这个才是防护手套对吧？
Because these are the gauntlets, aren't they?
长官！出事了！我觉得我被一辆马车给碾了！
Sir! Emergency! I think I've been run over by a cab!
抓住了
There you go.
碰一下就会失去最近一小时左右的记忆
One touch and you lose about an hour of your memory.
要是让它咬到你 那就是几十年的记忆
Let it bite you, and you could lose decades.
而你仍然没有逃跑
And you're still not trying to run.
我还是不明白那个雪人是怎么把自己堆出来的
I don't understand how the snowman built itself.
你解释清楚了我就跑
I'll run once you've explained.
什么克拉拉？
Clara who?
什么博士？
Doctor who?
噢 这个问题很危险
Oh, dangerous question.
危险有什么问题？
What's wrong with dangerous?
那种雪能发射低级心灵感应场
The snow emits a low level telepathic ...
我的雪人…
My snowman ...
貌似能反映人的思维和记忆
Seems to reflect people's thoughts and memories,
正因为这个特性 才形成了刚才的雪人…
and because it's unusual, somehow it carries a previous shape ...
等一下 博士！
No, Doctor!
是我那个雪人！
My snowman!
啊！有意思
Ah! Interesting.
对了 你刚刚在想着它么？
Well, were you thinking about it?
对啊
Yes.
那就别想了
Well, stop.
克拉拉 别再想着这些雪人了！
Clara, stop thinking about the snowmen!
趴下！
Get down!
克拉拉 听我说 这种雪正在吞食你的思维！
Clara, listen to me. The snow is feeding off your thoughts!
这不明白！
I don't understand!
你在它们的心灵感应场里 它们在映射你的想法
You're caught in their telepathic field. They're mirroring you.
你想得越多 它们出现的越多
The more you think about the snowmen, the more they appear.
你要想象它们在融化 想象一下 想出它们融掉的样子！
Imagine them melting. Picture it. Picture them melted!
很好 非常好 你做得非常非常的棒！哈！
Well, very good. Very, very good! Ha!
它们还会再出现吗？
Is that going to happen again?
这个嘛 如果再出现 你也知道怎么对付了
Well, if it does, you know what to do about it.
除非我失去记忆
Unless I forget.
不要来找我 忘掉我 听明白了吗？
Don't come looking for me. Forget about me. You understand?
这雪怎么办？我们不该提醒别人一下吗？
What about the snow? Shouldn't we be warning people?
那不是我的问题
Not my problem.
圣诞快乐！
Merry Christmas!
把她送回到我们遇见她的地方
Take her back where we found her.
是的 长官
Sir.
拜托啊
Come on.
哈喽
Hello.
是隐形的
Invisible.
隐形的楼梯
An invisible staircase.
有人吗？
Hello?
是谁？
是谁在这儿？
Hello?
今夜冰雪将要消融 但明天的雪会更猛烈地降临
Tonight the thaw, tomorrow the snow will fall again, yet stronger.
溺亡的女人和孩子的噩梦最终会赋予我们形体
The drowned woman and the dreaming child will give us form at last.
明日大雪将至 人类将会覆灭
Tomorrow the snow will fall, and so shall mankind.
冰雪之女即将成形！
She is coming!
看啊！雪一定是昨晚化掉的
Look at that! Must have thawed in the night.
求你了 克拉拉 我恳求你留下！
I'm begging you, Clara. I'm on my knees!
艾尔茜今天下午就会回来 我只是临时帮忙的
Elsie is back this afternoon, and I was only helping out.
我还有自己的工作要做
Got my own work to get back to.
什么工作？你为什么一直不告诉我们啊？
What work? Why won't you ever tell us?
我说了你们也不会相信
You'd never believe me.
艾丽丝 你今天气色不错啊！
Alice, how smart you look today!
家庭老师应该从后门进来
The governess should enter by the back door
除非是在带着孩子们的时候
unless accompanied by the children.
孩子们怎么样了？是不是一直期待着明天的到来呢？
And how are the children? Excited about tomorrow?
弗兰西斯卡还是老样子
Francesca, same as ever.
迪格比说他每天都在想你
Digby said he missed you every day.
拉提莫上校要见你一面
Captain Latimer wants to see you.
那是必然的
Of course.
每天都想？
Every day?
外加每周六想两次
Twice on Saturdays.
这还差不多
That's better.
拉提莫上校
Captain Latimer.
啊 蒙塔歌小姐你回来了
Ah. Miss Montague, you're back.
赶在圣诞前回来了
In time for Christmas!
很抱歉之前离开了一阵 但家人染病总是难料之事
Apologies for my brief absence -- family illness is so unpredictable.
您见我有什么事吗？
You wanted to see me?
弗兰西斯卡最近一直在做噩梦
Francesca has been having nightmares.
这对小姑娘来说也是常有之事
Young girls often do.
可她说这周每晚都是这样 而且她又不肯跟我谈谈
Every night this week, she says. Won't tell me about them.
或许您用更恰当的方式问她 她就愿意告诉您了
Perhaps if you asked her in the right way, there's no one she'd rather tell.
我对照看孩子这种事真的挺不在行…
Children are not really my area of expertise ...
但他们终究是您的孩子
They are, however, your children.
如果可以的话 我想说你在处理这类问题上非常有一套
You have, if I may say, a remarkable amount of wisdom in these matters,
尤其是对你这样漂亮的姑娘来说
for one so ... very pretty, Miss Montague.
年轻 我是说
Young, I mean.
我要去照看孩子们了
I'll see to the children now.
蒙塔歌小姐！
Miss Montague!
蒙塔歌小姐 你回来了！
Miss Montague, you're back!
应该怎么说呀？
Ah, ah, ah!
早上好 蒙塔歌小姐
Good morning, Miss Montague.
早上好 弗兰西斯卡 早上好 迪格比
Good morning, Francesca. Good morning, Digby.
你们不觉得圣诞前夜非常激动人心吗？
Christmas Eve is most thrilling day, don't you think?
现在跟我说说 我不在的这段时间你们都做了些什么吧
Now, what have you two been up to while I've been away?
我画了七幅画
I did seven drawings.
我们还看到了一头死掉的牛
And we saw a dead cow.
哦 真刺激呢！
Well, how exciting!
用你的秘密口音说两句嘛！
Do your secret voice!
大家好啊 伙计们！
(in cockney) 'Ello, mates!
也不完全是噩梦 就是一些梦而已
They're not exactly nightmares -- just dreams.
和我们那个死去的家庭教师有关
About our old governess -- the one who died.
她进了坟墓了都还纠缠着弗兰妮！
She's haunting Frannie from beyond the grave!
你们没有跟爸爸说这件事吗？
Haven't you spoken to your father about this?
这种事不可以跟爸爸说的
You can't talk about things like that to Daddy.
你应该试试的
You could try.
你想看看她死的那个地方吗？
Do you want to see where she died?
她掉进了这个池子 后来池子就结冰了
She fell in there, and then it froze.
她就被封在了冰里 就这样过了一天又一天
She was in the ice for days and days.
我不喜欢她
I hated her.
她老是爱生气
She was cross all the time.
弗兰妮梦见她还在冰层下面 等着重回人间
In Frannie's dream, she's still down there, waiting to come back.
其它地方的雪都化掉了 但这个池塘…
Everything else has thawed, but this pond ...
一直冰冻着
is still frozen.
这种雪会吞食你的思维
The snow's feeding off your thoughts.
你想得越多 它们出现的越多
The more you think about the snowmen, the more they appear.
弗兰妮 这很重要
Frannie, this is important.
你梦见她了 有些什么内容？
You dream about her. What do you dream?
她对我生气
She's cross with me.
她说我不乖了 她要从池子里出来处罚我
She says I've been bad, and she's going to come out of the pond and punish me.
什么时候？
When?
她说她会赶在圣诞节回来 也就是今晚
She said she'd come back for Christmas -- tonight.
我觉得弗兰妮是疯了 你不觉得吗？
I think Frannie's gone mad, don't you?
我觉得她需要一个医生(博士)
I think she needs a doctor.
博士！
Doctor!
她在找什么啊？
What's she looking at?
她好像在找一个医生
She's asking for a doctor.
博士！
Doctor!
行了 你的动静太大了！
Now, then, that's enough noise!
我们不想引起太多注意 明白吗？
We don't wanna attract attention, do we?
我在找博士 你们认识他吗？那个博士？
I'm looking for The Doctor. Do you know about him? The Doctor?
哪个博士？
Doctor who?
不要试图逃跑 否则你就会被消灭！
Do not attempt to escape or you will be obliterated!
我来给你把衣服放好吧？
May I take your coat?
坐下
Sit.
你们的世界有两种饮品是血红的颜色
There are two refreshments in your world the colour of red wine.
而且这杯可不是红酒
This is not red wine.
Vastra夫人会问你一些问题
Madame Vastra will ask you questions.
每个问题你只能用一个单词来回答
You will confine yourself to single-word responses.
只能一个单词 明白了吗？
One word only. Do you understand?
为什么？
Why?
真相往往形单影只 谎言则总是一套一套的说辞
Truth is singular. Lies are words, words, words.
你见过博士了 对吧？
You met The Doctor, didn't you?
对
Yes.
你现在又在找他了 为什么？
And now you've come looking for him again. Why?
慢慢想 只能用一个单词
Take your time. One word only.
好奇
Curiosity.
好奇什么？
About?
雪
Snow.
也好奇他这个人吧？
And about him?
是的
Yes.
你想找他做什么？
What do you want from him?
求助
Help.
为什么？
Why?
危险
Danger.
他为什么要帮你？
Why would he help you?
热心
Kindness.
博士现在并不热心
The Doctor is not kind.
不是吗？
No?
不是的
No.
博士不会帮助别人 再也不帮任何人了
The Doctor does not help people, not anyone, not ever.
他处于世事之外 不愿介入其中
He stands above this world and doesn't interfere in the affairs of its inhabitants.
他不是你们的救世主 也不是你们的保护神
He is not your salvation, nor your protector.
你明白我说的这些话吗？
Do you understand what I'm saying to you?
说辞
Words.
他曾经不是这样的 不过那是很久以前的事了
He was different once, a long time ago.
热心 没错
Kind, yes.
甚至可以说是英雄
A hero, even.
一个救世主
A saver of worlds.
但他失去太多 伤了他的心
But he suffered losses, which hurt him.
于是他现在宁可与世隔绝 也不愿让伤痛有重返的机会
Now he prefers isolation to the possibility of pain's return.
请体谅地选用一个词表达你对这件事的理解
Kindly choose a word to indicate your understanding of this.
人之常情
Man.
我们是博士的朋友
We are The Doctor's friends.
我们帮他与世隔绝地生活 但这不表示我们赞同他的做法
We assist him in his isolation, but that does not mean we approve of it.
所以 这是一个对你的考验
So ... a test for you.
给我一条你要传达给博士的信息
Give me a message for The Doctor.
告诉他关于这雪的一切 和它会带来的危险
Tell him all about the snow and what fresh danger you believe it presents,
最重要的是 解释清楚为什他要帮助你
and above all, explain why he should help you.
但是 只有一个单词
But do it in one word.
你一定在觉得不可能有这样一个词
You are thinking it's impossible that such a word exists
有的话你也难以找到
or that you could even find it.
就看看上天是否会眷顾你吧
Let's see if the gods are with you.
是我 什么事啊？我正试着读书呢！
Yes, what? Trying to read!
克拉拉小姐以及她对雪的担忧
Miss Clara and her concerns about the snow.
我对她进行了一句话测试
I gave her the one-word test.
这种事情没有什么意义
It's always pointless.
她说了什么？
What did she say?
喂？是什么？
Well? Well?
Pond
池塘
Strax已经提议要从哪里开始调查了
Strax has already suggested where to start investigating.
危险 危险！
Danger. Danger!
什么事？
What's wrong?
这里出现了危险因素
There is danger here.
有个智慧生物 超越这个时空所有生灵的智能体
An intelligence. An intelligence beyond anything else in this time and place.
西敏博士 有人要见您
Dr. Simeon, sir. There's someone demanding to see you.
说过这里不能有访客 他留下名字了吗？
No callers, not in here, not ever. Did he leave his name?
老爷…是歇洛克·福尔摩斯！
Sir ... it's Sherlock Holmes!
噢 不错的办公室 还有大圆球
Oh, yeah. Nice office. Big globey thing.
现在 别说话 什么也别告诉我！
Now, shut up. Don't tell me!
我从你的领扣看出来
I see from your collar stud
你有棵苹果树和一个瘸腿的妻子 我说对了么？
you have an apple tree and a wife with a limp. Am I right?
不对
No.
但是你有一个妻子对吧？
But you have a wife?
没有
No.
一几棵树？几个妻子？总有些苹果吧？
Bit of a tree? Bit of a wife? Some apples?
拜托 配合我一下嘛
Come on, work with me here.
我也爱看《海滨杂志》 也读过这篇小说
I enjoy The Strand magazine as much as The Next Man,
我很清楚歇洛克·福尔摩斯是个虚构人物
but I am perfectly aware that Sherlock Holmes is a fictional character.
出去！
Get out!
你有没有一条叫Colin的金鱼？
Do you have a goldfish named Colin?
没有
No.
我想也没有
Thought not.
回到正事 噢！我知道这是你的一张名片
Now ... Ooh! I see this is one of your business cards.
因为正面就写着
It says so on the front.
你是什么人？你在这里搞什么明堂？
Who are you? What are you doing here?
就是这个
This.
起来了 起来了！
Wakey, wakey!
那个设备可贵重得很！你离它远点
That is highly valuable equipment! You must step away now.
我们是极智体
We are the Intelligence.
噢！会说话的雪 我就是喜欢新奇的东西
Oh! Talking snow. I love new things.
你不属于这个世界
You are not of this world.
外星人正合适堆外星雪人
Takes one to SNOW one!
好了 我看看
Right. Let's see.
多核结晶状有机体 能够对模拟和映射周围事物
Multi-nucleate, crystalline organism with the ability to mimic and mirror what it finds.
看着像雪 又不是雪
Looks like snow. Isn't snow.
现在必须请你离开这里！
You must leave here now!
闭嘴！我正在演绎推理呢 真令人兴奋
Shut up! I'm making deductions. It's very exciting.
那么 你到底是何方神圣 啊？
Now, what are you, eh?
一大群太空晶体么？还是一大波？
A flock of space crystals? A swarm?
那些雪人只是小兵 一帮缺乏心智的掠食者而已
The snowmen are foot soldiers, mindless predators,
但是你不一样 你是聪明的一个 你是莫里亚提
but you -- you're the clever one. You're Moriarty.
于是你出现在一个星球上
So you turn up on a planet.
你产生心灵感应场 尽你所能去学习与了解
You generate a telepathic field to learn what you can.
等你了解得足够多了 又会怎么做呢？
When you've learnt enough, what do you do?
你不能用雪人去征服这个世界
You can't conquer the world using snowmen.
雪人一到七月就废了
Snowmen are rubbish in July.
你得比雪人更强才行 你必须进化
You'll have to be better than that. You'll have to evolve.
老爷 门好像卡住了！
Sir, it appears to be stuck!
你干了什么？是你把门锁上的吗？
What have you done? Have you locked the doors?
老爷！
Sir!
你需要把自己转化得更…人类
You need to translate yourself into something more, well, human.
把门踢开！
Kick it down!
要做到这一点 你需要一个完好的冰雪形态的人类DNA副本
To do that, you need a perfect duplicate of human DNA in ice form.
哪里能找到这种东西呢？
Where do you find that?
老爷？
Sir?
进来这里！快点！
Get in here! Quickly!
我找到一把总管钥匙了 老爷
Got a master key somewhere, sir.
现在只要查一下 最常打开的文件 最常浏览的页面
Now, let's see. Most opened file, most viewed page.
你知道吗 你应真该清空浏览记录的！
You know, you really should delete your history!
“家庭教师冰冻在池塘中”
Governess Frozen in Pond.
找到了！
Gotcha!
门打开了 老爷！
Got it, sir!
快进来 把他带下楼去
Get in here! Take him downstairs.
冰封在池塘里的尸体
Body frozen in a pond.
这样那雪就能够仔细观察一个人类 就像全身扫描一样
The snow gets a good long look at a human being, like a full body scan.
取到它们进化所需的所有信息
Everything they need to evolve.
一切都在池塘之中 猜得好 克拉拉
Pond. Good point, Clara.
你到这儿来干什么？
What are you doing here?
Vastra夫人想问问您是否需要手榴弹
Madame Vastra wondered if you were needing any grenades.
手榴弹？
Grenades?
她说的可能是“协助”
She might have said help.
协助什么？
Help for what?
这个 当然是帮你调查
Well, your investigation.
调查？谁说我在调查了？
Investigation? Who says I'm investigating?
你真以为
Do you think
因为某个小姑娘对我笑了笑 我就会开始调查了？
I'm gonna start investigating just because some bird smiles at me?
你以为我是什么人？
Who do you think I am?
歇洛克·福尔摩斯
Sherlock Holmes.
不要耍小聪明 Strax 一点都不适合你
Don't be clever, Strax. It doesn't suit you.
抱歉 长官
Sorry, sir.
我才是聪明的那个 你是像土豆的那个
I'm the clever one. You're the potato one.
是 长官
Yes, sir.
现在你可以走开了
Now, go away.
遵命
Yes,
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes.
喂！你住嘴！你不聪明也不有趣 你还有小短腿！
Oi! Shut up! You're not clever or funny, and you've got tiny little legs!
记好 就跟她说你要走了 不上楼了
Okay. Just tell her you're leaving, you're not going up.
要走 不上楼
Leaving, not going up.
怎么回事？五分钟后见？这个手势哪儿来的？你…
What was that all about? five minutes? Where did that come from? You ...
这不是研究所的那个雄性人类吗 他来这儿干嘛？
It's the human male from the institute. What's he doing here?
我提议我们先用酸液化了这货的脑子 再好好拷问他！
Suggest we melt his brain using projectile acid fish, and then interrogate him!
倒过来进行
Other way round.
我今晚还会做噩梦吗？
Am I going to have the nightmare tonight?
绝对不会了
Definitely not.
你怎么知道？
How do you know?
因为有人来帮忙了
Because someone's coming to help.
谁呀？
Who?
我说了你们也不会信的
You wouldn't believe me if I told you.
这又是你的一个故事么？你所谓的绝对是真的故事？
Is it one of your stories? Your definitely true ones?
喂！我的故事都是真的好不好
Huh! All my stories are true.
你在大本钟钟面后面出生那件事也是真的么？
Like how you were born behind the clock face of Big Ben?
所以我的时间观念才这么强嘛
Accounting for my acute sense of time.
你发明了鱼也是真的？
And you invented fish?
因为我不喜欢一个人游泳
'Cause I dislike swimming alone.
这次又是个怎样的故事呢？
So what's this one?
有这样一个人 他叫做博士
There's a man called The Doctor.
他住在天空中的云彩上面
He lives on a cloud in the sky.
而他一天到晚 日复一日所做之事
And all he does all day, every day,
就是让世界上所有的孩子们都不再做噩梦
is to stop all the children in the world ever having bad dreams.
可我还是做了噩梦啊
I've been having bad dreams.
那是因为他放假了
He's been on holiday.
不过 我确信他现在已经回来工作了
But, I am confident he's now returned to work,
事实上 他就在这里！
and as a matter of fact, he's right here!
是你吗 博士？
Aren't you, Doctor?
我的天啊！
Blooming hell!
孩子们最近很淘气嘛！
The children have been very naughty!
到我身后来 赶紧 快点！
Just get back. Now. Quickly!
你在用你的另一个种口音说话哦！
You're doing your other voice!
没错 亲爱的 你注意到了呢？
Yes, love. Did you notice?
你们这些淘气 调皮的小孩儿！
Naughty, naughty children!
快跑！
Run!
我们要怎么办啊？
What do we do?
弗兰妮 想像她融化的样子
Frannie, Frannie, imagine her melting.
你说什么？！
What?!
用你的想象 融化她！
In your head, melt her!
我不行啊！
I can't!
我真是受不了你们了！
I'm getting impatient!
你们最近真是淘气得要命！
You have been very naughty!
那个人在哪儿呢？你不是说那个住在云上的人就在这里吗？
What about the man? You said the man was here, the cloud man!
可他实际上不是没来吗？
Well, he's not, is he?
博士在哪里啊？
Where's The Doctor?
我也不知道！
I don't know!
博士啊？
Doctor?
博士呀？
什么博士？
Doctor who?
那样才像话！
That's the way to do it!
喂！
Oi!
嗷！
Ow!
她上哪儿去了？她还会回来吗？
Where did she go? Will she come back?
不会 别担心了 她正顺着你们的地毯往下渗呢
No, don't worry. She's currently draining through your carpet.
新增的抗冻设置 顺便说句不用客气
New setting, anti-freeze, and you're very welcome, by the way.
我真的很感激你 我就知道你会来的
I'm very grateful. I knew you'd come.
你才不知道 因为我都不知道
No, you didn't, because I don't.
我老早就不做这些事了
Because this isn't the sort of thing I do any more.
所以下回你要碰上什么麻烦的话可别指望我来…
Well, next time you're in trouble, don't expect me to ...
怎么了？有什么不对的吗？
What is it? What's wrong?
没事 就是…
All right. Just ...
我刚才都没注意到我戴上了这个
didn't know I'd put it on.
旧习难改啊…
Old habits ...
更冷了(更酷了)
It's cooler.
是啊 当然了 对吧？它最酷了
Yeah, it is, isn't it? It is very cool.
领结最酷了！
Bow ties are cool!
不是 我说的是这屋子 房间里越来越冷了
No, the room. The room is getting colder.
她又要恢复原形了！
She's coming back!
她要干什么啊？她要来处罚我吗？
What's she going to do? Is she going to punish me?
她已经学会了怎样保持不化
She's learnt not to melt.
当然了 她又不是个真的家庭教师 她是个怪物
Of course. She's not really a governess. She's just a beast.
她要来吃你们了
She's going to eat you.
快跑
Run.
孩子们 上面是什么在响…
Children, what is the exp ...
你是什么鬼？你在我家做什么？
Who the devil are you? What are you doing in my house?
不必惊慌 我是您家庭教师的绅士朋友
It's okay. I am your governess' gentleman friend.
我们刚刚是在楼上…
and we've just been upstairs ...
亲嘴呢！
kissing!
拉提莫上校 花园里有个雪人！
Captain Latimer, in the garden, there's snowmen!
它们都是自己突然冒出来的 看啊！
And they're just growing, out of nowhere, all by themselves. Look!
晚上好 我是来自远古世纪的蜥蜴女 这位是我的妻子
Good evening, I'm a lizard woman from the dawn of time and this is my wife.
这栋房子正遭受攻击！
This dwelling is under attack!
保持镇定 人类渣渣们！
Remain calm, human scum!
那么 有什么疑问吗？
So ... Any questions?
你有个…绅士朋友？
You have a ... gentleman friend?
Vastra 出什么事了？
Vastra, what's happening?
雪族已高度本地化 这些并不是自然降雪
The snow is highly localised, and on this occasion not naturally occurring.
这里的雪是从大门外停着的一辆马车里来的！
It's coming out of that cab parked by the gates!
长官 一个粉碎型手榴弹就能把这些雪人炸成渣渣！
Sir, one pulver grenade would blow these snowmen to smithereens!
它们是雪做的 Strax 它们已经是渣渣了
They're made of snow, Strax. They're already smithereens.
看到了吧 克拉拉？咱这位朋友
See, Clara? Our friends again.
克拉拉？克拉拉是谁？
Clara? Who's Clara?
您家现任家庭教师 实际上是个前酒馆女招待 她叫克拉拉
Your current governess is in reality a former barmaid called Clara.
那样才像话！
That's the way to do it!
与此同时 您家前任家庭老师现在
Meanwhile, your previous governess is now
是一个想到处揍人的活体冰雕！
a living ice sculpture impersonating Mr. Punch!
珍妮 你这儿有什么可以对付它么？
Jenny, what have you got?
这个应该可以拖住它
Should hold it.
长官 到这个房间里来
Sir, this room:
一扇瞭望窗口 还有一个易守的入口
one observational window on the line of attack and one defendable entrance.
没错 所有人都进去 赶紧动起来！你 抱她进去
Right. Everyone in there. Now! Move it! You, carry her.
很高兴看到你从云上下来 重问世事
Nice to see you off your cloud and engaging again.
我不是在重问世事 我是在遭受攻击！
I'm not engaging again. I'm under attack!
很怀念这种感觉 对吧？
You missed this, didn't you?
别瞎说！
Shut up!
Strax 我们还能撑多久？
Strax, how long have we got?
它们根本不打算攻击
They're not going to attack.
这些家伙毫不掩藏自己的行踪
They made no attempt to conceal their arrival.
攻击部队绝不会放掉这种出其不意的机会
An attack force would never abandon surprise so easily.
他们还组了个防守队形！
And they're clearly in a defence formation!
噢 对对对 干得好 小土豆！作战经验都还在啊老兄！
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. Well done, Straxie! Still got it, buddy!
长官 请不要在战斗准备阶段揉我脑袋！
Sir, please do not noogie me during combat prep!
所以说这里有它们想要的东西
So there's something here they want.
那个冰女人
The ice woman.
正是
Exactly.
她为什么这么重要呢？
Why's she so important?
因为她是个完好的冰晶形态的人类DNA副本
Because she's a perfect duplication of human DNA in ice crystal form:
这是雪族与人类融合的终极形态
the ultimate fusion of snow and humanity.
要在地球上生存 雪族就需要进化
To live here, the snow needs to evolve.
而她就是进化的蓝图 她就是雪族需要形成的形态
And she's the blueprint. She's what they need to become.
昨晚冰雪消融的时候 那个池塘的冰也化了吗？
When the snow melted last night, did the pond?
没有
No.
这就是永不消融的活体冰块
Living ice that will never melt.
如果雪族得到了楼梯上这个冰人
If the snow gets hold of that creature on the stairs,
它就能学会造出更多冰人
it will learn to make more of them.
最终会造出一个冰雪军团
It will build an army of ice.
到时候就真的是这个星球上人类的末日了
And it will be the last day of humanity on this planet.
好好待在这儿
Stay here.
喂 我让你待在里面的！
Oi, I told you to stay in there!
噢 我没听你的话
Oh, I didn't listen.
你倒是经常不听话
You do that a lot.
这也是你喜欢我的原因啊
It's why you like me.
谁说我喜欢你了？
Who said I like you?
我觉得你刚刚证明了
I think you just did.
是你吻我的好吗！
You kissed me!
你脸红了
You blushed.
而且我们刚刚还…
And we just ...
别说了！
Shut up!
把她放了 交给我们
Release her to us.
给你们五分钟时间
You have five minutes.
我们得把她弄出去 又要防止她落到雪族手上
We need to get her out of here, but keep her away from them.
怎么办？
How?
用这个 那么明显的事还要我解释吗？
With this. Do I always have to state the obvious?
外面的那些怪物到底是什么？
Those creatures outside -- what are they?
只要我把这玩意儿弄出去 它们就不会危害到你了
No danger to you, as long as I get that thing out of here!
你 进去 快点
You, in there. Now.
你要干么？
What are you doing?
我偷偷告诉你 我也不知道
Between you and me, I can't wait to find out.
好了 你把这儿的人都看好了 我就可以…
Right. If you look after everyone here, then I can ...
克拉拉？
Clara?
博士！
Doctor!
你真是傻透了！
That was stupid!
你刚刚也很傻！
You were stupid, too!
我可以傻 我很善长犯傻的！
I'm allowed. I'm good at stupid!
那样才像话！
That's the way to do it!
她为什么老是说那句话？
Why does she keep saying that?
是在模仿 而且还是随机地模仿
Mirroring. Random mirroring.
我们得到屋顶上去！
We need to get on the roof!
呜噢！不 不！是我抓你的手！我才是抓手的 一直是我！
Wooh! No, no! I do the hand grabbing! That's my job. That's always me!
过来！快点！
Come on! Quickly!
啊！
Agh!
你怎么了？
What are you doing?
我的裙撑卡在这儿了
My bustle is stuck.
你还穿裙撑？！
Your bustle?!
你真得把这身衣服脱了！
You're going to have to take those clothes off!
我不是那个意思…
I didn't mean ...
我明白
I know.
我就是说…
I just ...
我理解 我真的理解
I understand. I do.
那就好
Good.
那么 你到底有个什么计划？
Now, what's the plan?
谁说我有计划了？
Who said I've got a plan?
你当然有计划 不然你拿那个干什么
Of course you've got a plan. You took that!
也许是因为我犯傻了呢
Maybe I'm an idiot.
你才不傻 你机灵着呢 真的很机灵
You're not. You're clever. Really clever.
那你呢？你说说看 我有个什么计划
Are you? If I've got a plan, what is it? You tell me.
那样才像话！
That's the way to do it!
这又是一次考验么？
Is this a test?
没错
Yes.
那东西会怎么对付我们？
What will it do to us?
当然是杀了我们！
Kill us!
那样才像话！
That's the way to do it!
好了 快说吧 计划 我有计划吗？
So, come on then. Plan -- do I have one?
噢 我知道你的计划了 我全知道了！
Oh, I know what your plan is. I knew straight away!
骗人 你才不知道
No, you didn't.
我就是知道
'Course I did.
那就给我看看吧！
Show me!
我为什么要那样做？
Why should I?
因为不行动的话我们俩30秒内就会死掉
Because we'll be dead in under 30 seconds.
我有计划么？
Do I have a plan?
如果我们刚才是要逃 我们就该下楼才对
If we'd been escaping, we'd be climbing down the building.
如果我们刚才是要藏起来 我们也该躲到屋顶的另一边去
If we'd been hiding, we'd be on the other side of the roof.
但是我们没有 反而来到了这里
But, no! We're standing right here.
所以说呢？
So?
所以说嘛…
So ...
你先请
After you.
还是你先请
你就先上去吧 我穿着条裙子呢
After you -- I'm wearing a dress.
目视前方 小子！
Eyes front, soldier!
我一直是目视前方的好不好！
My eyes are always front!
我就不一定了
Mine aren't.
别闹！
Stop it!
才怪
No.
我听说你是前任家庭教师
I understand you're the previous governess.
遗憾地通知你 这个岗位已经换人了
I regret to inform you the position is taken.
晚安！
Good night!
这么说 你可以移动云朵？你能控制云朵？
So you can move your cloud? You can control it?
不能 没人能控制云朵 傻子才想控制云朵！
No, no one can control clouds. That would be silly!
风倒是可以稍微控制一下
The wind -- a little bit.
她还在跟着我们啊！
She's following us!
就是要那个效果 让她远离雪族！
That's the idea -- keep her away from the snow!
话说 你到底是酒馆女招待还是家庭教师？
So, barmaid or governess -- which is it?
让怪物追着跑的时候你还要闲聊？
That thing is after us, and you want a chat?
总不能等到被凶残地灭口了再聊吧？
Well, we can't chat after we've been horribly killed, can we?
我们怎么这么快就爬了这么高？
How did we get up so high so quick?
聪明的楼梯 里面比外面高的！
Clever staircase. It's taller on the inside!
我脚下的是什么？是什么做成的？
What am I standing on? What's this made of?
这是超高密度水蒸气 应该能暂时把她困住
Super-dense water vapour. Should keep her trapped for the moment.
这么说你真的住在这里？云上的盒子里？
So you actually live up here? On a cloud in a box?
已经住了好长一段时间了
I have done for a long time now.
我的天 你还真懂得让自己闷闷不乐
Blimey, you really know how to sulk, don't ya?
我没有在闷闷不乐！
I'm not sulking!
你都把自己关在一个小盒子里了！
You live in a box!
跟你做家庭教师相比关在盒子里算什么
That's no more a box than you are a governess.
噢 又是男人的口吻！这么说你跟其他人也没什么两样
Oh, spoken like a man! You know, you're the same as all the rest.
可爱的小克拉拉啊
Sweet little Clara,
在玫瑰与王冠酒馆打杂 却有更高的追求！
works at the Rose & Crown, ideas above her station!
我可告诉你 我骨子里才不是什么乖乖女
Well, for your information, I'm not sweet on the inside,
而且我在这个世界上也绝不…
and I'm certainly not ...
卑微渺小
little.
它叫TARDIS 可以穿行至任何一个时空
It's called the TARDIS. It can travel anywhere in time and space.
它是我的！
And it's mine!
可是它…
But it's ...
看啊！它明明就…
Look at it! It's ...
接着说吧 多数人都是那么说的
Go on. Say it. Most people do.
外面比里边小啊！
Smaller on the outside!
好吧 这种说法倒是头一回
Okay. That is a first.
是魔法吗？还是个什么机器？
Is it magic? Is it a machine?
它是艘飞船
It's a ship.
飞船？
A ship?
全宇宙最棒的飞船
Best ship in the universe.
里面有厨房吗？
Is there a kitchen?
又是头一回
Another first.
我也不知道自己干嘛问起厨房来了 只是…
I don't know why I asked that. It's just ...
我喜欢做蛋奶酥
I like making souffles.
蛋奶酥？
Souffles?
你为什么要给我看这些呢？
Why are you showing me all this?
是你自己跟来的 忘了吗？我可没有请你过来
You followed me, remember? I didn't invite you.
你都快比我高上一英尺了
You're nearly a foot taller than I am.
你根本不需要用这个就能够得到梯子
You could've reached the ladder without this.
你其实是为我准备的
You took it for me.
为什么
Why?
我从来不知道为什么
I never know why.
我只知道是为了谁
I only know who.
这是什么？
What's this?
我决定
Me.
重回这个世界
giving in.
我也不知道自己为什么会哭起来…
I don't know why I'm crying ...
我知道
I do.
记住此刻 现在记住此刻的一切
Remember this. Remember this right now, all of it.
因为就在今天
Because this is the day,
就是今天这个日子
this is the day,
今天是一切回归之日！
this is the day everything begins!
克拉拉！
Clara!
放开我！
Get off of me!
水蒸气根本挡不住冰 我早该意识到这一点的！
Water vapour doesn't stop ice. I should've realised!
放开！
Get off!
放开她 赶紧放开她！听见没有！
Let her go. Let her go now! Now!
放开我！
Get off of me!
克拉拉！
Clara!
不要啊！
No!
那是怎么回事？
What was that?
克拉拉摔下来了！
It's Clara!
上帝啊 噢 上帝啊 她是从哪儿摔下来的？
Dear God. Oh, dear God, where did she fall from?
未探测到生命迹象
我们得把她弄进屋里来！
We have to get her inside!
可那些怪兽会杀了你的！
Those things will kill you!
可她受伤了啊！
She's hurt!
她已经死了
She's dead.
那是什么声音？那又是怎么了啊？！
What is that? What is happening?!
博士把她接进去了
He's bringing her in.
那位绿皮肤的女士说她已经死了 那她现怎么还活着呢？
That green woman said she was dead. How can she be alive now?
此技术所拥有的性能和本领
This technology has capacities and abilities
是你等渺小的人类无法理解的！
beyond anything your puny human mind could possibly understand!
我是说你就别操心了
Try not to worry.
这冰人不是还很危险吗？它可能又会复原的
Isn't the creature still a danger? It could reform.
别担心 它在这儿复原不了
No, not in here.
那你现在该去看看克拉拉小姐
Then you should be with Miss Clara.
她会没事的 我知道的 她一定不能出事
She's going to be fine. I know she is. She has to be.
博士 她的伤势很严重
Doctor, her injuries are severe.
那个仪器一开动 谁都能再活一阵 但若要维持下来…
That equipment will bring back anyone for a while, but long term ...
都是我的错
It was my fault.
我要为克拉拉的遭遇负责 她当时是由我照看的！
I am responsible for what happened to Clara. She was in my care!
你这样自责又有什么意义？
What is the point of blaming yourself?
确实没意义
None.
因为她肯定会活下去
Because she's going to live.
嘿
Hey.
又见面了哦
Hello.
大家一定都觉得我要死了吧？
They all think I'm gonna die, don't they?
可我知道你会活下来的
And I know you're going to live.
怎么做？
How?
我从不知道怎么做
I never know how.
我只知道为谁而做
I just know who.
那位绿皮肤的女士…
The green lady ...
她说你曾是拯救过世界的人
she said you were the saver of worlds once.
那你还会拯救今天吗？
Are you gonna save this one?
如果我做到了 你愿意跟我一起走吗？
If I do, will you come away with me?
愿意
Yes.
那就好
Well, then.
祝你圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas.
我手上有冰雪之女的一块残片
I have in my hand a piece of the ice lady:
你们要造冰人的话 只要用它即可
everything you need to know about how to make ice people.
那就是你们要的东西吧？
Is that what you want?
想要就到你办公室来见我吧！
See you at the office!
这么说 博士你又要拯救世界了？我能问问是为什么吗？
So, then, Doctor, saving the world again? Might I ask why?
你是不是想和宇宙谈谈条件？
Are you making a bargain with the universe?
比如说你救下世界克拉拉就得以存活？
You'll save the world to let her live?
没错！你就不觉得
Yes! And don't you think,
这么多年来凭我所做的一切 还换不来这点补偿吗？
after all this time and everything I've ever done that I'm owed this one?
我只是觉得宇宙不会和你谈条件
I don't think the universe makes bargains.
可我的过失也不该殃及他人！
It was my fault!
行了
Well, then.
还是拯救世界要紧
Better save the world.
你承诺要交给我们的东西带来了吗？
You promised us something. Have you brought it?
你出去的这段时间这大个子挺安静的嘛
Big fella here's been very quiet while you've been out,
不过考虑到他的真实属性倒也合情合理
which is only to be expected, considering who he really is.
你知道这是什么吗 大个子？
You know what this is, big fella?
我并不理解这些标记
I do not understand these markings.
这是1967年的伦敦地铁路线图
A map of the London Underground, 1967.
要我说的话 就是都市的战略要害
Key strategic weakness in metropolitan living, if you ask me.
不过 我本来就不喜欢隧道…
But, then, I have never liked a tunnel ...
闲话说够了
Enough of this.
我们是个强大的族群 然而在这个星球上却行动受限
We are powerful, but on this planet we are limited.
我们需要学会模拟人类的形态
We need to learn to take human form.
那个家庭教师是我们的绝佳的复制品…
The governess is our most perfect replication of humanity ...
它的声音怎么变了？
What's happening to its voice?
它要蜕去伪装了
Just stripping away the disguise.
不要 停下来！别弄了！停下！我命令你停下！
No, stop! Stop that! Cease! I command you!
这声音听上去像个孩子
Sounds like a child.
当然听着像个孩子 它本来就是一个孩子
Of course it sounds like a child. It is a child.
是儿时的西敏 没有他的话雪族根本不能发声
Simeon as a child. The snow has no voice without him.
别听他瞎说 他是要毁掉这一切！
Don't listen to him. He's ruining everything!
极智体和你沟通有多久了？
How long has the Intelligence been talking to you?
从我小时候开始的 他是我堆的雪人 突然对我说话了
I was a little boy. He was my snowman. He spoke to me.
他们都好蠢
They're silly.
雪族是不会说话的 明白吗？它就像一面镜子
The snow doesn't talk, does it? It's just a mirror.
我不想跟他们说话 他们都好蠢
I don't want to talk to them. They're silly.
他们都好蠢
They're silly.
它只会反馈我们思考着 感觉到和恐惧的一切
It just reflects back everything we think and feel and fear.
我才不需要其他人
I don't need anyone else.
才不需要其他人
Don't need anyone else.
你把你最阴暗的梦境浇铸到了一个雪人当中
You poured your darkest dreams into a snowman.
现在你看到后果了吧！看看它成了什么样！
And look! Look what it became!
我还是不明白
I don't understand.
它就是个寄生物
It's a parasite
以一个孩童的孤寂和一个老人的病态为食
feeding on the loneliness of a child and the sickness of an old man.
当弱肉强食的雪族遇到了维多利亚时代的价值观
Carnivorous snow meets Victorian values ...
可怖之物便应运而生
and something terrible is born.
我们还可以继续 依照计划行事！
We can go on, and do everything we planned!
是啊 没错 什么样的计划呢——让冰人遍布全球
Oh, yes. And what a plan -- a world full of living ice people.
噢 真服了你了 你还真是领会了维多利亚时代的精髓！
Oh, dear me, how very Victorian of you!
维多利亚时代的价值观有什么不对吗？
What's wrong with Victorian values?
你确定要这样吗？
Are you sure?
我对此从来都坚信不疑！
I have always been sure!
那好吧
Good.
很高兴你这么想 毕竟你成人阶段的记忆就要不复存在了
I'm glad you think so, since your entire adult life is about to be erased.
没有宿主 就没有寄生者
No parasite without a host.
没有了你 极智体就不能说话
Without you, it will have no voice.
没有了那个家庭教师 它就失去了形态
Without the governess, it will have no form.
这 这是…什么情况？你都干了什么？
What, what ... What's happening? What's happening? What did you do?
你能映射的东西都不存在了
You've got nothing left to mirror any more.
再见！
Goodbye!
你到底做了什么…你是不是…
What did you ... Did you ...
你真以为我有这么容易对付吗？
Did you really think it would be so easy?
这不可能
That's not possible.
这怎么可能？
How is that possible?
博士！
Doctor!
他们又冒出来了！雪人又冒出来了！
They're growing! The snowmen are growing!
我们要怎么办？
What do we do?
可你只能是西敏博士 你不是真的 只是他虚妄的梦
But you were just Dr. Simeon. You're not real. He dreamed you.
你怎么能够继续存活？
How can you still exist?
梦境超越了造梦者的命数 就此得以永存
Now the dream outlives the dreamer and can never die.
曾经我只是受制于人的玩偶 而今我已掌控全局！
Once I was the puppet. Now I pull the strings!
想我苦心孤诣多年 只为拟出人类的形态
I tried so long to take on human form.
而今你抹去西敏的心智 竟给我提供了空间
By erasing Simeon, you made space for me.
此刻我就是他的灵魂！
I fill him now!
超越了冰雪之态 远胜西敏之流！
More than snow, more than Simeon!
这副躯体虽垂垂老矣 但在我的掌控下依旧有力
Even this old body is strong in my control.
你感觉到我族的力量了吗？
Do you feel it?
凛冬将至！
Winter is coming!
不行 你必须坚持！
No, you must fight!
坚持抗争 小子 你做得到的！
Hang on and fight, boy. You can do it!
拉提莫上校 你的孩子们…
Captain Latimer, your children ...
他们很害怕
they are afraid.
去抱着他们
Hold them.
这些事我真的不擅长
It's not really my area.
现在你必须学着点了
It is now.
又出什么状况了？
What's happening?
博士！看那个玻璃球！里面的雪都化成雨水了！
Doctor! The globe! It's turning to rain!
所有的雪都化了 看啊！
All of it, the snow. Look!
他死了 刚才到底发生了什么？
He's dead. What happened?
雪族只会映射他物 它只会这一件事
The snow mirrors. That's all it does.
现在它也是在映射另一种东西
It's mirroring something else now,
这东西十如此强大 以至于盖过了其他一切存在
something so strong it's drowning everything else.
上校家里刚才有大量的雪
There was a critical mass of snow at the house.
如果 如果说是那里的事件引起的话…
If, if something happened there ...
好咸 这雨水是咸的
Salty. Salt water rain.
这不是下雨 而是在流泪
It's not raining. It's crying.
地球上唯一可以盖过雪族的力量
The only force on Earth that could drown the snow:
一家人在平安夜的哭泣
a whole family crying on Christmas Eve.
很遗憾 我们已经回天乏术了
I'm sorry. There was nothing to be done.
她只能再坚持片刻
She has moments only.
我们拯救了这个世界 克拉拉 你我一起做到的
We saved the world, Clara, you and me.
我们真的成功了
We really, really did.
你还会回到…你那片云上吗？
Will you go back ... to your cloud?
现在已经没有云了
No more cloud. Not now.
为什么没有了？
Why not?
都化成雨水了
It rained.
快跑
Run.
跑吧 你这机灵鬼
Run, you clever boy.
还要铭记这一切
And remember.
现在是圣诞了
It's Christmas.
圣诞节真的来了
Christmas Day.
极智体一族怎么样了？也和雪一起消融了吗？
And what about the Intelligence? Melted with the snow?
我看没有 它们已经懂得如何超越实体存活了
No, I shouldn't think so. It learned to survive beyond physical form.
不过形神俱散的生物也不会有多危险
Well, we can't be in much danger from a disembodied Intelligence
何况它还以为用几个雪人就能入侵地球呢
that thinks it can invade the world with snowmen.
虽然他还了解伦敦地铁是一大战略要害
Or that the London Underground is a key strategic weakness.
奇伟之智…好像有点印象…
The Great Intelligence ... rings a bell ...
奇伟之智？
The Great Intelligence?
博士你想到什么了？
Doctor?
我从来都不知道她的全名
I never knew her name, her full name.
我是奥斯温·奥斯瓦尔德 Alaska号星际飞船的初级娱乐经理
Oswin Oswald, junior entertainment manager, Starship Alaska.
蛋奶酥女孩…
Souffle girl ...
是奥斯温 原来是她！
Oswin. It was her!
跑起来吧 你这机灵鬼
Run, you clever boy.
还要铭记
And remember.
又是蛋奶酥女孩！
It was souffle girl again!
最初在Daleks那儿我没看到她的长相 但那个声音…
I never saw her face the first time with the Daleks, but her voice ...
就是同一个声音啊！
It was the same voice!
博士你在说什么呀？
Doctor?
同一个女人！两次出现 两次都死了！同一个女人啊！
The same woman! Twice! And she died both times! The same woman!
博士 拜托了 你到底在说些什么啊？
Doctor, please. What are you talking about?
有些东西正在酝酿之中 不可思议 又…
Something's going on, something impossible, something ...
不说了 你们俩好好待在这儿 就原地待着 一动也别动
Right. You two stay here. Stay, stay right here. Don't move an inch.
你还会回来吗？
Are you coming back?
应该不会了！
Shouldn't think so!
你要去哪儿？
But where are you going?
去找她！去找克拉拉！
To find her! To find Clara!
可是克拉拉已经死了啊 他为什么还说要去找她？
But Clara's dead. What's he talking about -- finding her?
我也不明白 也许宇宙最终同意了他的条件
I don't know, but perhaps the universe makes bargains after all.
你要往哪儿走啊？
Where are you going?
抄近路
Short-cut.
从那儿走？我不喜欢这地方 你不觉得这儿很诡异？
Through there? I hate this place! Don't you think it's creepy?
谁说的 我才不信鬼魂
Nah, I don't believe in ghosts.
克拉拉！
Clara!
奥斯温！
Oswin!
奥斯瓦尔德！
Oswald!
看着我奔跑吧！
Watch me run!
下集预告
哈哈！想我了么？
Ha-ha! Miss me?
你这家伙是谁啊？
Who the hell are you?
我是博士 我来自外太空
I'm the Doctor. I'm an alien from outer space.
我已经一千多岁了 我有两颗心脏
I'm 1,000 years old. I've got two hearts.
但是我不会开飞机啊！
And I can't fly a plane!
你既然跟了盒子里的外星人 什么事都有可能发生
Running away with a spaceman in a box, anything could happen to you.
我还求之不得呢
That's what I'm counting on.
你想去哪里？
Where do you want to go, eh?
你想看些什么？
What do you want to see?
就是她吗？
Is that her?
死过两次的女人
The woman twice dead.
她还挺漂亮的 对吧？
She's rather pretty, isn't she?
她是个不可能的存在！
She's not possible!
言归正传 克拉拉·奥斯瓦尔德
Right, then, Clara Oswald.
是时候搞清楚你的前世今生了
Time to find out who you are.